Guide to the Edward Ostrander papers,1967-1977.
Ostrander, Edward papers, 1967-1977
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Edward Ostrander papers, 1967-1977.
23-16-3259.
Edward Ostrander.
4.4 cubic ft.
Bibliographies, site study proposals and reports, correspondence, clippings, articles, transcripts, memos, training materials, notes, photographic contact sheets, negatives.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library.
Documents Ostrander's study of architecture and planning in senior housing and its effect on the aged.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Professor in the Dept. of Design and Environmental Analysis, Cornell University.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Correspondence, publications, reports and subject files relating to Ostrander's work in gerontology and nursing homes, particularly the New York State Veterans' Home in Oxford.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Ostrander, Edward.; Cornell University--Faculty.; New York State College of Human Ecology. Dept. of Design and Environmental Analysis.; New York State Veterans' Home (Oxford, N.Y.).
Subjects:
Nursing homes--New York (State)--Planning.; Architecture and the aged.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
SERIES LIST
Series I. Gerontology Project: Six Site Study
A. Through 1970
Box 1, Folders 1-14
B. 1971
Box 1, Folders 15-30
C. 1972-1977
Box 1, Folders 31-42
Series II. New Nursing Home Conference
Box 1, Folders 43-48
Series III. Gerontology Project 103
Box 2, Folders 1-13
Series IV. Oxford Veterans' Home
Boxes 3, 4
Series V. Publications
Box 5
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I: Gerontology Project: Six Site Study
  - A. Pre 1970s-1970
    - Undated References - Bibliographies, Before 1971 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Background - Bibliography - Steidl, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Organizing Phase, November 1969-January 1970 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - College fund seeking, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Locations, stat summary sheets, BEH maps, transcripts, sample maps, symbol sheet (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Isabella Home Proposal - correspondence, site visit notes, background booklets, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Isabella Home - Background forms, observation data research maps, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Isabella Home Report: A case study - The Role of the Near Environment in Mediating Social Interaction in the Infirmary of a Geriatric Center, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Working Proposal - An Evaluation of the Relationship of the Physical Environment and the Aging Patient/Resident in the Long Term Care Setting, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Gerontology Newsletter, March-October 1970 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Potential Research/Design Report - by Van Alstyne, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Local senior housing clippings, 1969-1970 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - B. 1971
    - Correspondence, memos, minutes, proposals, January-April 1970 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Talk by Otto Fuchs for the seminar series An Environment for the Aging, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Workshop: "Housing for the Elderly: The Relationship of Environment to the Health and Well-Being of Older Persons", 1971 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Proposals - An Evaluation of an Exiting Environmental Interface with the Aging Person in a Rural Setting, 1971-1974 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Problem Comments and design solutions for all 6 sites - furniture, etc., 1971 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Ergonomics bibliography - Steidl and Nelson, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Student researchers training materials for 6 site study - prelim field practice, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Student researchers formal training session - schedule, script forms, site list, etc., 1971 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Confidential site reports - PECIIS pages, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Memos concerning the study, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Prelim-First visit - 02- Chenango Bridge data sheets, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Background info - 03 - Cortland, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Director's philosophy and background data sheets - 04- El Cor Nursing Home, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Prelim visit forms - 05 - Riverview Manor, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Prelim visit - 06 - St. Camillus, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Prelim visit - Director's Philosophy - first visit - 07 - Steuben Co. Infirmary, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Background data - first visit - 08 - Tompkins County Home, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Project Explanation, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - C. 1972-1977
    - Memos on behavior mapping report, project report, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Ellis Hollow/Groff Association - local activism, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Bethany Retirement Center, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Bethany Home - Horseheads, 1972-1973 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Burke Rehabilitation Center - correspondence and literature, 1972-1973 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Film proposal - resident options, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Transcriptions for the Housing Projects Series (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Gerontology issues, background reading lists and memos, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Ithacare Center brochures (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Speaker in the 406 Visiting Speaker Program - Robert Kastenbaum (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Grant proposal from College Special Projects Fund - with Ithacare and Bethany Retirement Home in Horseheads, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Searching for Gerontology Funding, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 42)
- Series II: New Nursing Home Conference
  - Proceedings, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Jaes Tunney's talk, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Ed Nokes' talk - Architect (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Arpie Shelton's talk - Isabella Home NYC -Director (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Post conference mailings, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Selected Readings for In-Depth Week - Understanding the Aging Individual in the Physical and Social Environment (Box 1, Folder 48)
- Series III: Gerontology Project 103
  - Data sheets, summary data (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - General material (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Contact sheets and negatives (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Work prior to New Nursing Home Conference and reports, 1970-1972 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Literature review forms, bibliography report (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Summer data sheets (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Facility 01 and 08 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Six site study facility 02 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Six site study facility 03 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Six site study facility 04 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Six site study facility 05 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Six site study facility 06 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Six site study facility 07 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Series IV: Oxford Veterans Home
  - Oxford Veteran's Home Proposal, November 1973-August 1974 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Budgets/Financial notes, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Annual Reports - Dorm Authority NYS, 1971-1974 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Architectural Firm Selections, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Post-visit notes, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1973-1974 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Physical background data: residents, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Staff Interview, 1973-1974 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Staff job descriptions (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - TAC/Health D/DEA/Oxf meeting transcripts, notes, 1973-1974 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - TAC/et al meeting transcripts, 1973-1974 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, notes, etc., 1974 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, notes, etc., 1974 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Tape inventory, meeting chronology, 1973-1974 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence, meeting notes, January-May 1974 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - L. Snyder - progress reports, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - L. Nahemow, consultant correspondence (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Oxford Publicity, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Oxford Main Report Copy - edited (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Oxford report original copy for February 4, 1974 first ½, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Oxford report original copy for February 4, 1974 2nd ½, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Oxford Post Occupancy Proposal items, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Oxford Signed Resident Consent Forms, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Photos, contact prints - people and site (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - History - Jack Smith's chronology notes (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - History - Jack Smith's notes (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - History - Jack Smith's interviews (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, notes, 1975 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Women's Relief Corp. Home Booklet 1907 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Typescripts from Norelco and meeting scripts (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Oxford Project staff travel requests (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - B.R. Cornell The Men at Oxford student reports (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - TAC Preliminary Activity Program, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Nahemow Report: Attitude Change with Institutionalization of the Aged, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Progressive Architecture, 1975 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Binghamton SUNY Report: Relocation Profile of Oxford Residents, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Health Facilities Codes, Rules and Regulations of the State of New York, 1969 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Oxford - Town and Village Comprehensive Master Plans, May 1969-February 1970 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Oxford Resident List and Staff list, 1973-1977 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Oxford - Relocation project forms - D. Slover (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Relocation info - Geon Pastalan (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Oxford Home - Report of fire safety survey, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Paper - System for Design of Typical Geriatric Facility Bedroom by Robert Steinbugler, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Oxford Proposal, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence re: Oxford Home, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence re: Oxford Home, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Training Material - Oxford Home, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Activity Forms - Oxford, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Agreement w/Dormitory Authority re: Oxford Home, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Health Facilities Directory, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Interview Data (residents ) Oxford Home, 1973 and 1974 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Oxford - Interim Report, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Reports - Oxford Home, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Memos and correspondence re: Oxford Home, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Memos and correspondence re: Oxford Home, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Oxford Newspaper, 1973 and 1975 (Box 4, Folder 31)
- Series V. Publications.
  - Papers and reports by the major contributors to the Gerontology Project: Steidl, Ostrander, Koncelik and Synder, early 1970s (Box 5)
  - Journal articles, reports, and other resource material from gerontology writers/researchers used as background info for the Gerontology Project (Box 5)